Jai Hind friends, I am Sanam Mishra and
welcome to my YouTube channel Sanam
Mishra Police. Friends, as you must have
seen and understood that today
we are going to talk about online exams.
So yes friends, this video is
especially for those who are going to give online exam for the first time
and they do
not know the ABC of the exam, how an online
exam is conducted. So today I will give them step
by step all the information about how
you have to give your exam. From reaching the exam center to
giving the exam, the whole
process till submitting it, today in this video I will
tell you how to select the option,
how you will know whether your
option has been selected, your submission has been done
or not,
you will get all this information in this video. So friends,
before moving ahead in my video, if
you have not yet subscribed to my channel,
then subscribe to the channel,
like the video and if you
want us to make a video for you on any topic, then
quickly
go to the comment section and comment. So let's go
and you  Let us tell you how to take the online exam,
so friends, first of all
you will reach the online exam center, on
reaching there you will be
sent to the exam hall,
now how will you know
which exam hall is yours, so as you
enter the exam hall, sorry exam center,
there your document
verification will be done first, your ID card etc. will be
checked, after that you will
get the lab number there, after the lab number, as soon as
you go further, your verification will be done there again,
your photo etc. will be clicked,
after that you will get the seat number, so
friends, as soon as you reach the exam center, this is how it happens, the
exam center
where you will be given your exam, so
this is the image you are seeing, this is the
photo of an exam center, which will be like this,
your computers will be installed there and in them
you can see that all of them are numbered
like 14 A 14 B 14 C
14 D, similarly you will be given the number starting
that in which hall you have to
go and sit on which number seat, so sir you will tell
you this thing  You'll be alerted, and then you'll have to
sit in your seat.
After you're seated, you'll find a seat like this. You can see that
after reaching the exam center and
sitting in your seat, you shouldn't talk to anyone. You should
n't talk to anyone sitting around you because if
you talk, you
could be thrown out of the exam center.
All the people on duty there keep
making rounds and
checking to see if
anyone is cheating or talking to each other. So,
you shouldn't talk to anyone even by mistake.
Now, you just have to focus on your PC
or computer. There are
instructions written on it. You have to read them. So, let's go
and see the complete steps. First,
a screen will appear in front of you.
As soon as the screen appears, you'll get
a password. You'll have to
enter your roll number. It tells you what
password you have to enter. If
you don't know the password,
a complete list of instructions will appear in front of you.  You have to
read it carefully, now
as if you are going to give the exam for the first time,
you do not know how to operate the computer, so
how do you have to enter and how do you have to
scroll all this, let me
tell you that, first of all friends, this is the mouse, this is
our mouse, it has 3 buttons,
one is the right button, one is the left button
and one is the scroll button, there are three
buttons in which we lack the
scroll button and the lift button, so
friends, the option is like when we
scroll here, then to scroll the entire question of the question,
you have to use this button up and down
and with the left button
you have to select the option and after
selecting the option, you will mostly find the
left button missing, you have to
click the left button, this is an easy
click, with this you have to
select the option, after that click on net,
you can scroll it like this
here and there and friends, let's talk about if you have to
enter your password, your
details, then for this
you will get the keyboard, the keyboard will be used only at
this time when  You have to enter your details,
after that there is no use of the keyboard, then you have to
lift the keyboard and keep it
up because it will disturb you again and again
and then after that you have to go to the
mouse and the process that I told you in the mouse is that
you have to click with the late button and
then after that the mouse will be used in it, so
friends, you have entered your details,
after entering the details, as soon as you will do OK,
you will see the
instructions, you have to read them carefully
because you have gone to give the exam for the first time, so
you have to read carefully what all is there, what is
given in the instructions, so as soon as
you click next after reading the instructions, on clicking next,
you will see the option there,
Hindi option is available and English
option is available, so just like it happened here also,
English is being shown in these, so
if you want, you want to
do Hindi, then you can do Hindi also, so
you change it from here, now the
option of both Hindi and English is available, so you have done it,
English is written now, please
read the following instructions carefully,
here you will see the instructions in Hindi, now the
instructions in English are available  They were visible, now they will be
visible to you in English. Here
I will tell you the most important thing in the instructions, number one you have
not yet answered the question, this is the instruction for this, the
second number will show red color, you have
not answered the question, it means
relief and the third number means
green color, on that you will get
that you have answered the question, the fourth
number you will see in purple color, it
means you have not answered the question
but have marked the question for reconsideration,
so I will tell
you how to mark it for reconsideration in this way
in the next video, after that whatever is there, we will
move ahead, this time you will see that the clock has been set on the server
and you will see the
countdown timer on the right corner of the head, the
time for completion of the exam will keep on being
displayed, so as soon as you
click on next, now all these
steps are done, now from here you have
read and understood the instructions and
computer hardware lot, you are in
progress, now you have to next it,
as soon as you next, the processing will start,
now you have to next it
when your  When the examiner says yes, you have to
click on the next button, only then you have to say
ok I am agree,
until your examiner says I am ready,
you do not have to click on begin, like when your
examiner will tell you that the exam is about to start,
now you click, then you
click, after that the processing will happen,
after the processing your exam is about to start,
so you will see this kind of processing
and after some time you will
see a screen like this, here you can see
that your first question has started showing here
and if you look above, here you are seeing the
time lift, it means 29 minutes are left for the
children, this time has gone in reverse,
like if you have a 2 hour exam, 3 hour exam
or 1 hour exam, then the
clock for that runs in reverse, it keeps showing this many minutes for the
children, so from here
you will come to know how much
time you have left, after this you see what I
told you, red color, red color means you have
not answered this question yet, so as soon as
you answer this question, how can you  If you want to answer,
you have to do it by pressing the left button,
after that as soon as you
click on and next,
you will
reach the second question and this
symbol which is visible here will turn green,
see and next you click on, then as soon as you click on next, the
first number means
you have answered, now here is the second
question, so when it is the second question, now you will
select it, whichever option seems
correct to you, after that you will click on next,
now if it is the third question, as
I told you, when will it turn purple, so
if this question is not becoming a question,
you feel that you have to think about it later and
answer a little, then
you will click on this option which is visible, then
mark it, you will click on review and next option and as soon as
you proceed,
see it will start showing in purple color, this will happen that
when you submit your test
or you will also review your entire
question, then you will understand here that
yes, now it  I have not
given the answer, so friends, let's go and
see it live in the entire screen once more, so
this is done, with this you have to scroll the mouse,
select the question, whatever is its
answer, after that click on next, as soon as you
click on next, see that
your answer has been selected, it starts showing green,
meaning you have given the answer, now
select the second option by selecting the second option
and then as soon as you click
next, the second option will also turn green, in this way
your entire exam will be completed, now as soon as
your time is about to end,
you will be told that the time is about to end,
submit it, so you can note change
your answer after you submit the test is ready, you can submit it in the
test and submit your answer, so here if you
want to go back to check something in the test, then
you can go advisory, you
can submit, so for this
you will just press the test and exit button,
your exam will be done
and after that if you submit, your exam will be
cleared, meaning you have submitted the entire exam,
now after this your result will be out
as soon as you click on the submit button  Let's click on it, there will be a
little frying, your exam will be
submitted and then you will see a message like this, congratulations, congratulations,
see you in the next video, till then
Jai Hind Jai